Guide to the Sylvia O'Brien Papers AIA.054
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sylvia O'Brien Papers
1940-2008
1955-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
O'Brien, Sylvia, 1924-2006
AIA.054
15.5 Linear Feet in 15 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
Sylvia O'Brien (1924-2006) was a Dublin-born, New York-based actress who starred in Broadway theater productions, as well as commercials and television programs. A member of Actor's Equity Association, the Screen Actors Guild, and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), O'Brien appeared in numerous Broadway productions, including a role as Mrs. Peace in the 20th anniversary production of My Fair Lady. This collection consists of diaries, playbills, photographs, correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, original writings, and scripts for various performances. The majority of the collection documents her professional career as an actress, including contracts, photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, a large collection of playbills, and files on individual productions she participated in. The collection also documents her personal life, including diaries, correspondence, a large number of personal photographs and photograph albums, and her original poetry and short stories.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sylvia O'Brien (1924-2006) was a Dublin-born, New York-based actress who starred in Broadway theater productions, as well as commercials and television programs. O'Brien was born in the Rathmines suburb of Dublin, Ireland in 1924 and emigrated to the United States in 1959 following her involvement with the travelling Irish Festival Singers. In 1959, she married Richard Seadar, the American road manager for the Irish Festival Singers tour. A member of Actor's Equity Association, the Screen Actors Guild, and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), O'Brien appeared in numerous Broadway productions, including a role as Mrs. Peace in the 20th anniversary production of My Fair Lady. In addition to her acting career, O'Brien also wrote poetry and short stories, many of which were published in American and Canadian magazines. She died in 2006.
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the personal and professional life of Sylvia O'Brien, and consists of diaries, playbills, photographs, correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, original writings, and scripts for various performances. The majority of the collection documents her professional career as an actress, including contracts, photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, a large collection of playbills, and files on individual productions she participated in. The collection also documents her personal life, including diaries, correspondence, a large number of personal photographs and photograph albums, and her original poetry and short stories.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Bruce Seadar, Sylvia O'Brien's husband's nephew and the executor of her estate, in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.038.
Related Archival Materials
Actors' Equity Association Records (WAG 011)
American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) New York Local Records (WAG 282)
Separated Materials
Approximately 1 linear foot of published books were separated to the library collection for cataloging.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series, all of which are arranged alphabetically:
Series I. Theater Files
Series II. Personal Materials
Series III. Original Writings
Color photographs.; Scripts (documents); Black-and-white photographs.; Diaries; Correspondence.; Actresses -- United States.; Irish Americans; Writings (document genre); Playbills.
- Series I. Theater Files, 1942-1994; 502536
  Scope and Content Note
  This series documents O'Brien's professional life as an actress and her interest in the performing arts, beginning with her involvement in the Irish Festival Singers to her later Broadway roles. Major productions include Da, Me and My Girl, and My Fair Lady. Materials include playbills, photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and scripts for various performances.
  - Broadcasting (Radio Eireann), 1954-1963; 502537 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Commercials, Sep 1976; 502538 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dressing Room Door Plate for Da, 1965; 502539 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dublin Programs, 1942-1957; 502540 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - "Imagination" Radio Series on Irish Writers, 1972-1975; 502541 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Irish Festival Singers, 1955-1993; 502542 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Photographs: Cast Photographs and Headshots, 1955-1979; 502545 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Photographs: Dressing Room, undated; 502546 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Theater, 1958-1979; 502548 (Box 1, Folder 17-18, Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Photographs: Theater Photo Album, 1944-1977; 502549 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Playbills: #s, circa 1950-1999; 502551 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Playbills: A, circa 1950-1999; 502553 (Box 1, Folder 22-28)
  - Playbills: B, circa 1950-1999; 502556 (Box 2, Folder 1-7, Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Playbills: C, circa 1950-1999; 502557 (Box 2, Folder 8-18)
  - Playbills: D, circa 1950-1999; 502558 (Box 2, Folder 19-25)
  - Playbills: E, circa 1950-1999; 502560 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Playbills: F, circa 1950-1999; 502561 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Playbills: G, circa 1950-1999; 502562 (Box 3, Folder 7-13)
  - Playbills: H, circa 1950-1999; 502563 (Box 3, Folder 14-19)
  - Playbills: I, circa 1950-1999; 502564 (Box 3, Folder 20-23)
  - Playbills: J, circa 1950-1999; 502565 (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Playbills: K, circa 1950-1999; 502566 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Playbills: L, circa 1950-1999; 502567 (Box 4, Folder 4-10)
  - Playbills: M, circa 1950-1999; 502568 (Box 4, Folder 11-19)
  - Playbills: N, circa 1950-1999; 502569 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Playbills: O, circa 1950-1999; 502570 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 4, Folder 22-24)
  - Playbills: P, circa 1950-1999; 502571 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
  - Playbills: R, circa 1950-1999; 502572 (Box 5, Folder 6-12)
  - Playbills: S, circa 1950-1999; 502573 (Box 5, Folder 13-29, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Playbills: T, circa 1950-1999; 502574 (Box 6, Folder 2-6)
  - Playbills: U, circa 1950-1999; 502575 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Playbills: V, circa 1950-1999; 502576 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Playbills: W, circa 1950-1999; 502577 (Box 6, Folder 10-15)
  - Playbills: Y, circa 1950-1999; 502578 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Playbills: Z, circa 1950-1999; 502579 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Print Work, 1966-1970; 502580 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Productions: Anta, 1962; 502581 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Productions: Beggar's Opera, Oct 1964; 502582 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Productions: Cabaret, 1977-1978; 502583 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Productions: Conduct UnBecoming, Oct 1970; 502584 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Productions: Da, 1978-1979; 502585 (Box 6, Folder 23-26)
  - Productions: Dear Oscar, 1972; 502586 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Productions: Every Other Evil, 1961; 502587 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Productions: The G.B.Essence of Woman, Dec 1964; 502588 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Productions: Hadrian VII, 1968; 502589 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Productions: Harlequinade, Dec 1960; 502590 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Productions: Hedda Gabler, 1981, 1994; 502591 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Productions: How to Survive a Marriage, 1974-1975; 502592 (Box 7, Folder 1, Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Productions: The Killing of Sister George, 1967-1968; 502593 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Productions: Law and Order, 1998-2002; 502595 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Productions: The Loves of Cass McGuire, 1966; 502596 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Productions: McBain, Oct 1995; 502597 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Productions: Me and My Girl: Broadway, Jan 1989-Sep 1989; 502598 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Productions: Me and My Girl: National Tour, 1988-1989; 502599 (Box 7, Folder 8-10)
  - Productions: Molly Maguires, 1965-1968; 502600 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Productions: The Mundy Scheme, 1969; 502601 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Productions: My Fair Lady: Art Park, 1987; 502602 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Productions: My Fair Lady: Papermill, 1976-1977; 502603 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Productions: The Natural Look, 1967; 502604 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Productions: O Marry Me, Oct 1961; 502605 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Productions: Poetry in 3D, 1966; 502606 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Productions: Possession, 1986; 502607 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Productions: Returnings, 1983; 502608 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Productions: The Right Honourable Gentleman, 1965; 502609 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Productions: Sylvia Carroll's Broadway, 1966; 502610 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Productions: Two's Company: Series 1, 1957-1958; 502611 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Productions: Two's Company: Series 2, 1958; 502612 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Productions: Two's Company: Series 3, 1959; 502613 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook, undated; 502614 (Box 7, Folder 25-26)
  - Scripts: Beginning to End (Jack MacGowan), 1970; 502615 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Scripts: A Corner of the Bed (Allan Jack Lewis), 1968; 502616 (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
  - Scripts: Cry, Tiger (Mel Weiser), 2008; 502617 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Scripts: Currer Bell, Esquire (William Luce), 1980; 502618 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Scripts: Dolly West's Kitchen (Frank McGuinness), circa 1999; 502619 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scripts: The Duel (Jack Dell), 1968; 502620 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scripts: Esther the Queen ("Abel Drugger"), 1961; 502621 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scripts: Hedda Gabler (Henrik Ibsen/Rolf Fjelde), undated; 502622 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Scripts: Hold Out Your Hand, 1970; 502623 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Scripts: The Killing of Sister George (Frank Marcus), 1964; 502624 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Scripts: The Loves of Cass McGuire (Brian Friel), undated; 502626 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Scripts: The Natural Look (Lee Thuna), 1967; 502627 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Scripts: The Passion of Josef D. (Paddy Chayefsky), 1963; 502628 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Scripts: Returnings (Richie Allan), 1985; 502630 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Scripts: The Right Honourable Gentleman (Michael Dyne), 1965; 502631 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Scripts: Toys in the Attic (Lillian Hellman), 1960; 502633 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Sheet Music, undated; 502635 (Box 9, Folder 1-2, Box 8, Folder 14-17)
  - Soap Operas, 1985-1987; 502636 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Theatrical Reviews, 1960-1973; 502637 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
- Series II. Personal Materials, 1945-2000; 502638
  This series consists of diaries, correspondence, memoranda, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other materials documenting O'Brien's personal life and interests. The majority of the series consists of 40 years of her diaries, which she entitled "Sylvia's Musings." In her diaries, O'Brien discusses both personal and professional matters, including her daily activities, marriage, friendships, vacations, family history, and social activities; her thoughts of various current events and social issues; and her reflections of professional matters, including auditions, particular aspects of individual productions, as well as interactions with cast members, crew, and theatrical management. The series also includes biographical and genealogical information, scrapbooks, personal photographs, and subject files on issues of interest to O'Brien.
  - 50 Art Songs (Schirmer), 1956; 502639 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ais-Eiri Interview, 1980; 502641 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Information, undated; 502643 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Birthday Cards, 1945-1954; 502644 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Christmas Cards, 1984-2000; 502645 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: General, 1990-2004; 502648 (Box 9, Folder 12-14)
  - Diaries: Jun 1955-Aug 1955, 502649 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Diaries: Aug 1959-Dec 1966, 502651 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Diaries: May 1961-Aug 1961, 502652 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Diaries: Apr 1962-May 1967, 502654 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Diaries: Jul 1966, 502656 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Diaries: Jun 1967-Dec 1968, 502657 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Diaries: Mar 1969-Oct 1970, 502658 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Diaries: Feb 1971-Dec 1971, 502659 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Diaries: Feb 1971-Feb 1972, 502661 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Diaries: Feb 1972-May 1973, 502662 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Diaries: Jul 1973-Aug 1973, 502663 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: Mar 1974-Dec 1975, 502664 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Diaries: May 1975-Dec 1975, 502665 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Diaries: 1976, 502666 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Diaries: Mar 1978-Nov 1978, 502667 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Diaries: Nov 1978-Apr 1979, 502668 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Diaries: Apr 1979, 502669 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Diaries: 1980, 502671 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Diaries: Mar 1980, 502672 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Diaries: Jan 1981-Oct 1981, 502673 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Diaries: Jan 1982-Nov 1982, 502674 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Diaries: Jun 1982 (Ireland), 502675 (Box 10, Folder 15, Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Diaries: Sep 1981-Nov 1982, 502738 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: Jun 1982-Jul 1984, 502739 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Diaries: Oct 1982, 502740 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Diaries: 1982, 502741 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Diaries: Mar 1983-Oct 1983, 502742 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Diaries: Oct 1983-Nov 1983, 502743 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Diaries: 1984, 502744 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
  - Diaries: Jan 1985-Apr 1985, 502745 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Diaries: May 1985-Sep 1985, 502746 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Diaries: Oct 1985-Dec 1985, 502747 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Diaries: Jan 1986-May 1986, 502748 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Diaries: Jun 1986-Dec 1986, 502749 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Diaries: Sep 1986-Oct 1986, 502750 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Diaries: Jan 1987-Apr 1987, 502751 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: May 1987-Aug 1987, 502752 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Diaries: Aug 1987-Sep 1987, 502753 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Diaries: Sep 1987-Feb 1988, 502754 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Diaries: Feb 1988-Apr 1988, 502755 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Diaries: May 1988-Jul 1988, 502756 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Diaries: Jul 1988-Dec 1988, 502757 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Diaries: Nov 1988-Jan 1989, 502758 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Diaries: Jan 1989-Aug 1989, 502759 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Diaries: Sep 1989-Dec 1989, 502760 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Diaries: Jan 1990-May 1990, 502761 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Diaries: May 1990-Jun 1990 (Greece), 502762 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Diaries: Jun 1990, 502763 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Diaries: Jul 1990-Sep 1990, 502764 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: Oct 1990-Dec 1990, 502765 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Diaries: Jan 1991-May 1991, 502766 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Diaries: May 1991-Sep 1991, 502767 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Diaries: Oct 1991-Dec 1991, 502768 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Diaries: Jan 1992-Mar 1992, 502769 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Diaries: Jun 1992-Nov 1992, 502770 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Diaries: Nov 1992-Dec 1992 (South Pacific), 502771 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Diaries: Dec 1992, 502772 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Diaries: Dec 1992-Jan 1993 (South Pacific), 502773 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Diaries: Jan 1993-Jun 1993, 502774 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Diaries: Jul 1993-Dec 1993, 502775 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Diaries: Jan 1994-Jun 1994, 502776 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Diaries: Jun 1994-Aug 1994, 502778 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Diaries: Sep 1994-Dec 1994, 502779 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: Jan 1995-Jun 1995, 502781 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Dockrell, Maurice, 1960-1968; 502783 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Feis Scrapbook, 1950-1953; 502784 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Genealogy: Grey Family Documentation, 1964-1987; 502788 (Box 14, Folder 7-10)
  - Genealogy: Immigration Documents, Sep 1960; 502790 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy: Leo O'Brien Marriage, 1963-1964; 502791 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Lady Gregory, 1968; 502792 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Howth Castle Research, May 1985; 502793 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Irish American Organizations, undated; 502794 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Journal of Books Read, 1953-2003; 502795 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Joyce, James, 1982, undated; 502797 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988-1997; 502798 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Obituaries, 1991-2006; 502799 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - O'Casey, Sean, 1977-1997; 502800 (Box 14, Folder 20-21)
  - O'Neill, Moira, 1971-1973; 502801 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Photographs: Personal, 1946-1966; 502802 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Photographs: Personal, 1944-1984; 502803 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Photographs: Personal, 1965; 502805 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Photographs: Personal, 1969; 502806 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Photographs: Personal, 1970; 502807 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Photographs: Personal, undated; 502808 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Photographs: Personal (Dios Class), undated; 502811 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Photographs: Personal (Florida and Caribbean), 1967-1968; 502810 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Photographs: Personal (Vacations), 1960, undated; 502813 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - Photographs: Photo Album, 1940-1948; 502814 (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - Photographs: Photo Album, 1950; 502816 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Photo Albums, undated; 502817 (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
  - Political Affiliations and Opinions, 2003-2005; 502819 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
  - "Song Tour of Ireland", 1955-1957; 502820 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Sugihara, Yukiko, 1995; 502821 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Tree Planting for Kitty O'Callaghan, 1986-1987; 502823 (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
  - Val Vousden Recitations, circa 1945; 502826 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Yeats, William Butler, Apr 1975; 502828 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Series III. Original Writings, 1960-1987; 502829
  This series consists of research notes, drafts, typescripts, and published versions of O'Brien's articles, poetry, and short stories.
  - Article on Dublin, 1973-1987; 502830 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Article on Sean O'Casey, undated; 502832 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Articles (Published), 1960-1970; 502833 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Creative Writing Class, Feb 1985-Mar 1985; 502834 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Early Drafts, undated; 502835 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - "Kate and the Spider", undated; 502836 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - "Music", undated; 502837 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Poetry: General, 1985-1987; 502838 (Box 15, Folder 21-23)
  - Poetry: Published, 1985-2001; 502839 (Box 15, Folder 24-26)
  - Publication Acceptances, 1984-1986; 502841 (Box 15, Folder 27-28)
  - Short Stories, undated; 502842 (Box 16, Folder 1-3, Box 15, Folder 29)
  - "Speaking", undated; 502843 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - "Vacancy" (Short Story Version), 1974; 502844 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "Vacancy" (Teleplay Version), 1974-1976; 502845 (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
  - Writings in Progress, 1979, undated; 502846 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Unprocessed (Box 20, Box 21, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 22)